Venable sister
I've been practicing celibacy and
keeping the precepts for quite some time
and trying to follow the advice of the
Buddha in terms of being watchful of
intentions behind my actions
not acting out of unwholesome mental
States but I have a problem that I would like
but I have a problem that I would like
to ask I've always been easily agitated
and prone to anxiety
and this Remains the case despite my
efforts when these mental States arise it is
when these mental States arise it is
hard to maintain perspective and I
sometimes act out of them without
realizing it at that time
it's mostly small things like speaking
without reflecting or making mistakes in
tasks because of being anxious and in a
rush but the more I try to prevent this it
but the more I try to prevent this it
seems like it just gets worse and I'm
even becoming agitated over trying to
not be agitated what am I doing wrong
and how can I correct this
um in this case you're worried about
unpleasant mental States like agitation
and anxiety but you can also look as
other things that you might be doing
um
like when things are are Pleasant for
example or when there is a pleasant
experience waiting for you are you
utilizing in that are you going for that
are you acting out of other things
um or laziness or or doubt or or other
um
kind of points that mean this if you're
basically letting the door open for
um
for hindrances on any occasion that
means that you're basically training
your minds to leave the door open so so
for example you know it's actually quite
a good a good point like if you find
yourself lapsing
and now
there's the you realize oh no actually I
I lapsed on that occasion and
and now your mind wants to kind of
revolve around that and try to figure
out how the hell will I not do it again
and how will I make myself not do it
again you can realize oh this is an
occasion where there's an unpleasant
mental feeling and now I just really
want to get rid of this so that's where
you have to see okay now it's the same
thing that I'm feeding basically the
same anxiety that is the reason that I
might act out of anxiety and lapse again
so
so if you find yourself lapsing on a
certain occasion you have to basically
accept the pain of knowing that you have
lapsed like there is consequences and
results of good and bad actions okay
this is the consequence of that bad
action this is an unpleasant feeling
that's very basic and kind of easily
overlooked thing
but if you just start okay I have to
accept that
then the next time the opportunity comes
when there's an unpleasant feeling
pressuring me for example
I might be better able to train myself
in in regard to it and not act out of it
because I've been training myself before
so it's basically not to kind of worry
about particular types of unpleasant
feelings or a particular
um
oh
types of different
actions that you might do on account of
them but start to kind of see through
them to any type of unpleasant feeling I
shouldn't be just feeling Justified and
trying to get rid of it like okay I know
I'm I know theoretically I'm not
justified in acting out of agitation or
acting out of anxiety but now when
there's the unpleasant feeling of
remembering I laughed I feel justified
in trying to do something to get rid of
that and trying to make it go away so
that I won't lapse again
but you have to realize that it's all
basically rooted in the same thing if
you start to see it that way you
basically start to then
um
become uh
uh
more independent in general and to be
able to
um
see by yourself how you can correct
these things because you're not
um just determining what is a lapse or
what is a good action for example on the
basis of what it resulted in oh on that
time I spoke with that it's like all
that time I made a mistake and this
resulted in that all of that becomes
irrelevant it's just okay if I was
trying to get rid of an unpleasant
feeling if I was delighting in a a
pleasant feeling that in itself is a
good enough reason to to not act out of
it that's what constitutes on wholesome
fundamentally and so that becomes your
criteria and that way then you can
always know at the moment when you're
about to act
it doesn't matter what else is going on
or what else is happening in the
situation or how
like how agitated the situation might be
like I don't know I'm in a rush to go to
the airport and this is going on and
that's going on doesn't matter it's like
what is the what is my saved with mind
at this moment and what's making me do
this action no matter what kind of
other thoughts or justifications I might
have first